Guide to the Walt Whitman papers, 1841-1940, bulk 1841-1891 RL.01378
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1841-1891 and undated
  - Manuscript Poems, circa 1855-1882 and undated
    - Leaves of Grass
      - "THE Poem ( ? One grand, eclipsing poem Poem of Materials" (Volume 15)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one sheet of green paper, about 6x5 inches. Recto: seventeen lines. Verso: "recommendation to the young men of all The States"; sixteen lines, much revised. Bound in a duodecimo volume, half green morocco. Notes on subject matter for poetry, containing phrases* which appear in "Starting from Paumanok," section 6, and Mediums" (Camden Edition, vi, 190-191); verso, a prose fragment dealing with political independence.
      - "?Gliding" (Volume 233)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of paper, about 11x6 inches, one side only; eight verses. Bound in a small folio volume, cloth, orange morocco back. A fragment describing street and interior scenes somewhat similar to those in "Outlines for a Tomb" (Camden Edition, iii 284).
      - All that we are—the solid and liquid we are, we have advanced to (Volume 234)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of yellow paper, about 12 x 6 inches, one side only; fifteen verses, with numerous revisions in pencil and ink. Bound in a small folio volume, cloth, undyed morocco back. An early draft of a poem (Camden Edition, iii, 257-258); the last three verses contain verbal parallels with a line or two of "Pictures."
      - "Theme for piece poem An opera" (Volume 22)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on both sides of a sheet of ruled paper, about 10 x 8 inches; twenty-six lines. An outline for a poem on various types of music, containing ideas apparently used in "Proud Music of the Storm" and "The Mystic Trumpeter."
      - "Corrections Proud music of the Storm" (Volume 23)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on a piece of ruled paper, 15x5 inches, one side only; thirty-three lines. Notes and phrases to be used in correcting "Proud Music of the Storm."
      - "And now it seems the dark, uncut hair of graves" (Volume 1)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written on six pieces of ruled paper, of various sizes. Recto: forty-three verses, in pencil, extensively revised. Verso: "The most immense part of Ancient History is altogether unknown"; forty-five lines, in ink, with numerous revisions. Inserted in a quarto volume, cloth, blue morocco back. An early draft of portions of "Song of Myself," chiefly sections 6 and 7, and a prose fragment containing a number of the ideas and phrases which appear in "Unnamed Lands" (Camden Edition, vi, 49-50).
      - "To be at all—what is better than that? " (Volume 2)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of ruled paper, about 7x6 inches. Recto: nine verses, with revisions in ink. Verso: "Sweet flag Sweet fern illuminated face clarified unpolluted"; about twenty-five lines, revised in pencil. Bound in a small quarto volume, cloth, orange morocco back. A fragment of verse, closely related to section 27 of "Song of Myself," and published posthumously as "To Be At All" (Inclusive Edition, page 462); with a list of words and ideas for use in heaves of Grass (Camden Edition, vii, 11; iii, 280).
      - "It is no miracle now that we are to live on always" (Volume 3)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of ruled paper, about 7x6 inches. Recto: about seven verses, revised. Verso: "After all is said and done in the way of argument"; twenty lines, revised. Bound in a small quarto volume, cloth, white pigskin back. An early version of certain ideas on touch used in "Song of Myself," sections 28-30 (Inclusive Edition, page 568), and a preliminary prose rendering of ideas later embodied in Leaves of Grass (Camden Edition, vi, 42).
      - "Light and air!" (Volume 4)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one side of a sheet of ruled paper, about 5x8 inches; twelve lines, revised. Bound in a quarto volume, cloth, orange morocco back. An early draft of verses intended for "Song of Myself," and used in part in section 31 (Camden Edition, iii, 261).
      - "[Fa]bles, traditions, and formulas are not animate things" (Volume 6)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of ruled paper, about 7x8 inches. Recto: fifteen verses, much revised. Verso: "It is the endless delusion of big and little smouchers"; twenty lines, revised. Bound in a quarto volume, cloth, brown morocco back. An early version of section 41, "Song of Myself (Inclusive Edition, page 578), and a portion of a paragraph dealing with the advantages taken "over the vast retinues of the poor" (Camden Edition, vi, 145).
      - "My Spirit sped back to the times when the earth was fiery mist" (Volume 7)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one sheet of ruled paper, about 7x7 inches. Recto: fourteen verses, extensively revised in pencil and ink. Verso: six cancelled words, "Not one of the heavier great." Bound in a quarto volume, cloth, brown morocco back. An early version of several lines now found in various portions of "Song of Myself" (Inclusive Edition, page 580).
      - "There is no word in any tongue" "Such boundless and affluent souls... bend your head in reverence" (Box 20)
        Description from Frey: Two autograph manuscripts, written on two sheets of ruled paper, about 7x8 inches, one side only. The first is a fair copy of fourteen verses, in green ink, with one pencilled revision; the second consists of nineteen lines, written and revised in ink. Mounted and framed with a photograph. A fragment of verse on God as revealed in man, in which appear several ideas and verbal expressions used in sections 48 and 49 of "Song of Myself" (Inclusive Edition, page 582); a prose fragment dealing with "boundless and affluent souls" and the pictures made by nature for man (Camden Edition, vi, 144).
      - "Broadaxe—First as coming in the rough ore out of the earth" (Volume 227)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one side of a sheet of ruled paper, about 13 x 8 inches; in three parallel columns, about four hundred words. Bound in a small folio volume, cloth, brown morocco back. Suggestions and ideas for "Song of the Broad-Axe" (Inclusive Edition, pages 612-614).
      - "Poem (subject) ? for recitation" (Volume 18)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written on three sheets of ruled paper, about 7x5 inches. Recto: about fifty lines, in ink and pencil. Verso of second sheet: "You occult, deep Volitions"; nine verses, written in pencil and extensively revised in pencil and ink. Bound in a small quarto volume, half orange morocco. Notes for a poem on outdoor cries, such as those of drovers, whalers, etc. (Camden Edition, vi, 198-199), and an early draft of a portion of "Song of the Redwood-Tree," section 1.
      - "I see who you are, if nobody else sees, nor you either" (Volume 8)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil with numerous revisions on one sheet of ruled paper, about 5x8 inches. Recto: nine verses. Verso: "Now for a legend not old, but as new as the newest on the spread'g land"; one verse. Bound in a quarto volume, half blue morocco. A version of certain ideas modified considerably prior to final use in "A Song for Occupations" (Inclusive Edition, page 623), with a single verse on the back of the sheet (Camden Edition, iii, 272).
      - "Perfect serenity of mind... Superior nonchalance" (Volume 194)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one side of a scrap of paper, about 1x6 inches; seven verses. Mounted and framed with a photograph. Two ideas partly used in "A Song of Joys" (Inclusive Edition, pages 611-612).
      - "In—This is the Earths word" (Volume 193)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one side of a piece of paper, about 4x6 inches; eight lines. Mounted and framed with a portrait of Whitman. A prose note setting forth a theme for a poem, probably "A Song of the Rolling Earth" (Camden Edition, vi, 141).
      - "Proem" (Volume 16)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one side of a sheet of ruled paper, about 7x7 inches; four verses. Bound in a quarto volume, cloth, yellow morocco back. An early draft of verses on sights in Manhattan, personality, egotism, and the equality of woman, possibly adapted for use in "Starting from Paumanok," section 12 (Camden Edition, iii, 263).
      - "O Mother, did you think there could ever be a time when I might not" (Volume 13)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on four pieces of paper, about 6x4 inches. Recto: about twenty-one verses, extensively revised. Verso: "man boy child infant youth young man"; lists, in two parallel columns, about two hundred words. These four sheets were mounted by Whitman on two sheets of green paper, about 5x6 inches, upon which twenty-five lines were written and revised in ink: "The American people, ever sturdy, ever instinctively just." In a small quarto volume, boards. An early version of portions of "This Compost," especially section 1; with lists of words representing divisions of the human family and various parts of the body, apparentlyused as reminders in preparing the 1856 version of "I Sing the Body Electric" (Camden Edition, vii, 22-23). The date 1856 appears twice on the manuscript. The prose fragment written on green paper is a discussion of Vigilance Committees in California (Camden Edition, vii, 23-24). With a clipping from an 1856 newspaper containing an account of events in California and a report on the proceedings of the seventh day of the session of the American Association for the Advancement of Science.
      - "I know as well as you that Bibles are divine revelations" (Volume 5)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of ruled paper, 8x7 inches. Recto: twelve verses, extensively revised. Verso: "Bill Guess.... Peter.... George Fitch"; twenty-four lines. Bound in a quarto volume, cloth, white pigskin back. A discarded version of lines intended for "Song of Myself," section 41 (Inclusive Edition, pages 577-578); and biographical notes, dated "March 20th '54," on three men, two of them drivers of horse-cars (Camden Edition, vi, 133-134).
    - Poems Not Appearing in Leaves of Grass
      Listed alphabetically by headings.
      - "[All] Hands Ro[und]" (Volume 24)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one side only of two sheets of green paper, about 8x7 inches; approximately thirty-five verses, extensively revised. An unfinished version of a patriotic song, employing rhyme and metre.
      - "I am not content now with a mere majority. ... I must have the love of all men and all women" (Box 20)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one side of a sheet of pink paper, about 3x6 inches; two verses. Mounted and framed with a portrait. (Camden Edition, iii, 285.)
      - "I am that half grown angry boy, fallen asleep" (Volume 25)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written on one sheet of ruled paper, about 8x8 inches. Recto: seven verses, written and revised in ink. Verso: "Municipal legislation, unitg examples in high place, is always inclined"; twenty-one lines, in pencil. Bound in a quarto volume, boards. A fragment of poetry (Camden Edition, iii, 280) apparently connected in idea with the prose story, "Of a summer evening a boy fell asleep" (see page 18, number 2); a portion of an essay on municipal legislation.
      - "Poem of Existence" (Volume 230)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one sheet of paper, about 12 x 9 inches, one side only; twenty-nine lines. Bound in a quarto volume, half green morocco. A fragment dealing with time, the interior of the earth, the stars, and the isolation of life from the non-living; the whole seems to be in a state halfway between prose and the finished product (Camden Edition, iii, 263-264).
      - "Remembrances I plant American ground with" (Volume 27)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of ruled paper, about 5x6 inches. Recto: seven revised verses. Verso: "Europe"; a list, in three columns, about 11o words. Bound in a small quarto volume, boards. A version of ideas recurring frequently in Leaves of Grass (Camden Edition, iii, 256); a list of rivers and cities Generated of Europe, some of the names of cities being followed by figures for their population (Camden Edition, vi, 217).
      - "Scantlings" (Volume 202)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one side of a piece of paper, about 4x5 inches; six verses, much revised. Mounted and framed with a photograph of Whitman and a printed copy of the poem. An apparently complete poem, dealing with the race of "scantlings" —"scant of muscle" —but nevertheless "from the strong growth of America" (Camden Edition, iii, 258- 259).
      - "Thought" (Volume 28)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on the back of a partly clipped proof sheet of the 1856 Leaves of Grass containing the beginning of "Sun-Down Poem" (later called "Crossing Brooklyn Ferry"), about 5x7 inches; seven verses, extensively revised. Bound in a quarto volume, cloth, white pigskin back. A draft of an apparently complete poem (Camden Edition, iii, 284-285).
    - Notes for Poems
      - Fragments and Ideas for Poems (Volume 29)
        Description from Frey: Fourteen autograph manuscripts, written in ink and pencil on scraps of paper of various sizes; about ninety lines in all. Mounted in a quarto volume, cloth, green morocco back. Headings: "The most Jubilant Triumphant Poem" (Camden Edition, vii, 24-25); "Poem of a proud, dar'g joyous expression—for Manhattan island!" (vii, 22); "Poem of the Black person" (vii, 19); "Poem" (vi, 142); "Poem of Poets (now) in all lands" (vii, 18); "Poem (bequeathing to others a charge) what poems are wanted" (vii, 28); "National hymns, real American music" (iii, 268); "Songs (written for the voice) (with notes)" (vii, 25); "Poem of (the Devil" (vii, 21); "Poem of Sadness" (vii, 20); "And there, farther south, the early negro at daylight call'g his brethren together" (iii, 284); "The Scout" (vii, 34); "Drops of my Blood" (vii, 33); "In a poem make the thought" (vii, 18). On the verso of "National hymns" are written two verses on hunters; on the verso of "Drops of my Blood" two verses in which Whitman addresses young men on the subject of poetry.
      - Notes for Poems (Volume 30)
        Description from Frey: Eleven autograph manuscripts, written in ink and pencil on scraps of paper of various sizes; about eighty-eight lines in all. Mounted in a quarto volume, cloth, green morocco back. Headings: "Poems identifying the different branches of the Sciences" (Camden Edition, vii, 20-21); "The Body" (iii, 277); "Poem of Language" (vii, 35); "Whole Poem —Poem of Insects?" (vii, 25); "Poem of Ohio, Kentucky, Indiana and Illinois" (vii, 28); "To the English and the French of Canada"; "Poem of Wisconsin" (vii, 19); "Poem of Fruits & Flowers" (vii, 21); "?The Carpenter's and Mason's Poem" (vii, 24); "Song of the Future" (vii, 24); "Poem. As in Visions of ... at night" (vii, 15). Germ ideas for poems and, in a few cases, partial elaboration or suggestions for expanding the germ ideas. Two clippings, describing life in the vicinity of Puget Sound, are mounted on the last piece of manuscript.
      - Outlines for Poems (Volume 31)
        Description from Frey: Fourteen autograph manuscripts, written in pencil and ink on scraps of paper of various sizes; about eighty-three lines in all. Mounted in a quarto volume, cloth, green morocco back. Headings: "Theory of a Cluster of poems the same to the passion of Woman-love" (Camden Edition, vi, 150); "A poem which more familiarly addresses those who will, in future ages understand me" (vi, 31); "?Poem of The Husband" (vii, 11); "Religious Canticles" (vii, 20); "Secrets. —Secreta" (vii, 35); "Companions" (vii, 28); "Poem of Young Men" (vii, 21); "An After-Thought or Two, and After-Songs" (vii, 26); "Poem, as in a rapt and prophetic vision" (vii, 34); "Poem ante-dating, anticipating, prophecying [sic] great results" (vii, 19); "Poem L'Envoy" (iii, 286); "Banjo Poem"; "Poem ? The Cruise ? A Cruise" (vii, 30); "of Death —the song of Immortality and Ensemble" (vii, 22). On the verso of "Religious Canticles" appear two verses and a portion of a third, an early version of a part of "[Hours Continuing Long, Sore and Heavy-Hearted]" (iii, 287).
      - Preliminary Studies for Poems (Volume 32)
        Description from Frey: Five autograph manuscripts, written on six pieces of ruled paper, about 5x8 inches. Bound in a quarto volume, cloth, orange morocco back. (1) "Picture of the most flow'g grandeur of a man"; thirteen lines, in pencil. Verso: "steamboats and vaccination, gunpowfder] and spinning-jennies"; nineteen lines, written and revised in ink. Notes for a description of a great man (Camden Edition, vi, 140), and a prose fragment dealing with the necessity of man's rising above folly and "artificial science" (vi, 140-141). (2) "Bloom"; six lines, in pencil. At the bottom of the sheet is pasted a scrap of manuscript, four lines in pencil, headed: "The Broad-axe —the axe of the headsman." A character sketch of a cartman named Bloom (Camden Edition, vi, 142), and a germ idea for "Song of the Broad-Axe." (3) "What we call Literature is but the moist and wobbling cub"; six lines, in pencil, slightly revised. A prose fragment on literature (Camden Edition, vi, 33). (4) "How gladly we leave the best of what is called learned and refined society"; thirty lines, written in ink on two sheets of paper, one side only, and revised in pencil. A prose fragment dealing with the pleasures of association with men who live outdoors (Camden Edition, vi, 151-152). (5) "Remember that the clock and the hands of the clock"; twelve lines in pencil, revised. A prose fragment on time (Camden Edition, vi, 203). Various portions of this and the above pieces seem to have been used in the writing of Leaves of Grass.
      - Suggestions for Poems (Volume 33)
        Description from Frey: Nine autograph manuscripts, written in ink and pencil on scraps of paper of various sizes; eighty-two lines in all. Mounted in a quarto volume, half brown morocco. Headings: "A poem in which is minutely described the whole particulars and ensemble of a first-rate healthy Human Body" (Camden Edition, vi, 106); "Remember in Scientific and similar allusions —that the theories of Geology" (vi, 3); "A volume —(dramatic machinery for localities, characters, etc.)" (vi, 149); "It seems to me—to avoid all poetical similes" (vi, 6); "What shall the great poet be then?" (vi, 4); "The most superb beauties are in the cheapest" (vi, 150); "Make no quotations, and no reference to any other writers" (vi, 4-5); "Breath and Spray" (vn, 34); "Poemet" (vii, 33). Ideas for poems and other literary enterprises, bits of advice to be followed in composition, and lists of titles and synonyms.
  - Manuscript Prose, 1852-1891 and undated
    Includes manuscript drafts and revisions of stories, prefaces, essays, lectures, Whitman's commentary on his own literary work and on that by other authors, autobiographical material, and a section of miscellany that consists of notes made on various subjects, the most prominent among them being travel and intellectual history. The fragments in each group are listed alphabetically by headings.
    - Stories
      Listed alphabetically by headings or titles.
      - "distinctness every syllable the flounderer spoke" (Volume 191)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of ruled paper, about 10 x 8 inches, one side only; thirty-two lines, with revisions. Mounted and framed with a photograph of Whitman. A portion of a short story (Camden Edition, vi, 132-133).
      - "Of a summer evening a boy fell asleep" (Volume 56)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on five sheets of thin brown paper, about 8x6 inches, one side only; eighty-seven lines, slightly revised. Bound in a small quarto volume, half orange morocco. An apparently complete short story (Camden Edition, vi, 146-148). See page 13, number 31.
      - "This singular young man was unnoted for any strong qualities" (Volume 38)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on two sheets of ruled paper, about 11x8 inches, one side only; sixty-one lines, revised. Bound in a small folio volume, cloth, undyed morocco back. An early short story, apparently complete (Camden Edition, vi, 130-132, 135).
    - Prefaces
      - "Camden—Phila April 8, '84" (Volume 47)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in purple pencil on one sheet of paper, about 12 x 6 inches, one side only; twenty-five lines, revised. Bound in a small narrow folio volume, half orange morocco. A description of the poet's years in Camden, apparently intended as part of a preface. On the verso appears a note by W. S. Kennedy: "Apparently for a projected new 2 vol. ed. of his Works.—W.S.K."
      - "Eidolons Preface Two Rivulets p 12" (Volume 62)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink, with revisions in ink and pencil, on six sheets of paper, about 7x5 inches, one side only; about 130 lines. Verso of fourth page: "A song no more of—a song of the good green grass"; three verses, written in pencil and revised in ink. Bound in a royal octavo volume, half blue morocco. A fragment partly used by Whitman in the preface to Two Rivulets, 1876, with an early draft of the opening lines of "The Return of the Heroes," 1871 version.
      - "for Dem Vistas" (Volume 58)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one side only of four sheets of paper, about 6x4 inches, and one small scrap; seventy-one lines, extensively revised. Bound in a duodecimo volume, cloth, green morocco back. Rough notes for a preface to Democratic Vistas (Camden Edition, vi, 16-17).
      - "The name of this tells much of the story—Before and Afterward" (Volume 63)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on four sheets of light brown paper, about 9x6 inches, one side only; sixty-four lines, revised. Bound in a royal octavo volume, half brown morocco. An early draft of portions of a preface (Camden Edition, vi, 17-19).
      - "(Of the great poet) (Finally) For preface" (Volume 69)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on three sheets of paper, about 9x5 inches, one side only; fifty lines, revised. Bound in a royal octavo volume, cloth, green morocco back. Notes based in part on the 1855 preface and intended for a later introduction (Camden Edition, vi, 30-31, 160-161, 162).
      - "Struggling steadily to the front not only in the spirit of Opinion" (Volume 50)